# **Matthew Rees**

**Applied Ecologist** 

**Curriculum Vitae** September 2020 **♀** School of Biosciences, University of Melbourne

matthewreesearch.com

+61 412 560 534

matt.wayne.rees@gmail.com

@matt\_w\_reesmatt-w-rees

in matthew-w-rees

#### **Profile**

I use quantitative methods to improve conservation monitoring, management and decision-making. I specialise in modelling population dynamics and species interactions, focusing on predator ecology and invasive species management. My computational toolkit is largely made up of GIS, structured decision-making tools, spatial capture-recapture, occupancy models and generalised additive models. I'm well-versed in field ecology which motivates me to consider what is feasible on-ground and fits within socio-economic constraints. More broadly, I'm passionate about transparent science which also considers the needs and knowledge of First Nations People. I am currently finishing up my PhD with the *Quantitative and Applied Ecology group* (supervised by Brendan Wintle, Bronwyn Hradksy & Alan Robley) while tackling the occasional, related contracting job.

# **Education**

2017-present PhD (Conservation Biology)
Interactions between invasive predators and native prey

2013-2016 Bachelor of Environmental Science (1st class Honours)
Prioritising invasive animal management in the Lake Eyre Basin, Australia

Queensland University of Technology

# **Professional Experience**

2019-2020	Ecologist (private contractor)	Winda-mara Aboriginal Corporation, Treetec	
	Training Indigenous rangers in fauna monitoring protocols and grant writing		
2020-2020	Research assistant Designing fox density field surveys	University of Melbourne	
2018-2020	<b>Demonstrator</b> Conservation Biology, Environmental Risk Assessment subjects	University of Melbourne	

## **Publications**

# Peer-reviewed

- 1. MW Rees, J Carwardine, A Reeson and J Firn (2020). Rapidly assessing cobenefits to advance threat-management alliances. *Conservation Biology*. https://doi.org/10.1111/cobi.13490
- 2. **MW Rees**, JH Pascoe, BA Wintle, M Le Pla, EK Birnbaum and BA Hradsky (2019). Unexpectedly high densities of feral cats in a rugged temperate forest. *Biological Conservation*, 239, 108287. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biocon.2019. 108287

#### In peer-review

- 1. H Davies, Tiwi Land Rangers, **MW Rees**, D Stokeld, A Miller, G Gillespie and B Murphy. Variation in feral cat density between two large adjacent islands in Australia's monsoon tropics. *Austral Ecology*.
- 2. M Le Pla, EK Birnbaum, **MW Rees**, BA Hradsky, AR Weeks, A Van Rooyen and JH Pascoe. Genetic sampling and an activity index indicate contrasting lethal control outcomes. *Journal of Wildlife Management*.

#### Reports

1. **MW Rees** (2020). Monitoring and managing critical weight range mammals in the indigenous protected areas of the world heritage Budj Bim cultural landscape. A report prepared for the Victorian Government, Department of Environment, Land, Water and Planning.

# Awards

2017	Victorian Government, Department of Land, Environment, Land, Water and Planning, PhD top-up scholarship	\$15K
2017	Australian federal government, RTP PhD scholarship	\$98K
2016	Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation, honours top-up scholarship	\$10K
2015	University of Wollongong, undergraduate research scholarship	\$7.2K

# **Grants**

2020	University of Melbourne, School of Biosciences, Jasper Loftus-Hills award	\$2.25K
2020	University of Melbourne, School of Biosciences, travel grant	\$2K
2020	Ecological Society of Australia, Hoslworth research endowment	\$7.5K
2019	Ecological Society of Australia, Hoslworth research endowment	\$6.75K
2018	Conservation Ecology Centre student scholarship	\$5K
2017	Victorian Environmental Assesment Council, Bill Borthwick scholarship	\$2K
2017	Victorian Government, Parks Victoria research partners program (co-investigator)	\$20K
2017	Victorian Government, Department of Land, Environment, Land, Water and Planning research grant	\$15K

#### **Presentations**

- ➤ International Statistical Ecology Conference (virtual), June 2020. Using spatial mark-resight and GAMs to infer predator interactions.
- ➤ Guest lecture, University of Melbourne, Australian Wildlife Biology, May 2020, Invasive mammals in Australia.
- ➤ Ecological Society of Australia, Launceston, November 2019, Does fox control increase feral cat population density?
- ➤ Wimmera Biodiversity Seminar, Rupanyup, September 2019, *Interactions between invasive predators and threat-* ened native mammals in south-west VIC.
- ➤ Otway Threatened Species Forum, Geelong, August 2019, Interactions between invasive predators and threatened native mammals in the Otway Ranges.
- ➤ Victorian Biodiversity Conference, Melbourne, February 2019, Prioritising invasive animal management in the Lake Eyre Basin to benefit both threatened species and agriculture.
- ➤ Ecological Society of Australia, Brisbane, November 2018, Modelling invasive predator density in mesic forests.
- ➤ Otway Threatened Species Forum, Geelong, August 2018, How many feral cats are there in the Western Otway Ranges?
- ➤ Mathematics of Biological Systems Symposium, Melbourne, April 2018, *Integrating co-benefits into the cost-effective prioritisation of conservation strategies*.
- ➤ Victorian Biodiversity Conference, Melbourne, February 2018, How many feral cats are there in the Western Otway Ranges?
- ➤ Environmental Institute of Australia & New Zealand conference, Brisbane, August 2017, Building alliances between the agriculture and conservation sectors.

#### Media

09/12/2019	Radio interview	ABC Melbourne	Invasive predators interactions
20/09/2019	Television segment feature	TF1 French National News	Invasive animals in Australia
08/08/2019	Radio interview	3AW	Invasive predators in south-west VIC
08/08/2019	Newspaper article (front page)	Geelong Advertiser	Invasive predators in south-west VIC
07/08/2019	Radio interview	ABC South West Victoria	Invasive predators in south-west VIC
13/03/2019	Newspaper article	Colac Herald	Feral cat density in the Otway Ranges
11/03/2019	Radio interview	ABC Melbourne	Feral cat density in the Otway Ranges
11/03/2019	Live TV interview	ABC news	Feral cat density in the Otway Ranges
10/03/2019	Online news article	ABC news	Feral cat density in the Otway Ranges
10/03/2019	Radio interview	ABC Ballarat	Feral cat density in the Otway Ranges

# **Service**

- ➤ Peer-reviewer, Wildlife Research, Conservation Biology and Austral Ecology scientific journals (2019-present).
- ➤ Social media manager, QAECO lab twitter account (2019-present).
- ➤ Award judging panel member, Ecological Society of Australia (2020).
- ➤ Treasurer, Biosciences Postgraduate Society (2019-2020).

#### **Referees**

- ➤ Prof. Brendan Wintle, PhD supervisor, b.wintle@unimelb.edu.au
- ➤ Dr Bronwyn Hradsky, PhD supervisor, bronwyn.hradsky@unimelb.edu.au
- ➤ Dr Alan Robley, PhD supervisor, alan.robley@delwp.vic.gov.au
- ➤ Dr Jack Pascoe, Collaborator, jack@conservationecologycentre.org